Finding aid to the Arthur Henry Pierce Papers CA.MS.00340
Smith College Archives
Arthur Henry Pierce Papers
1900-1914
Smith College Archives
Pierce, Arthur Henry, 1867-1914
CA.MS.00340
2.083 linear feet (5 containers)
Professor of psychology. Contains research, lecture notes, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Henry Pierce was born July 30, 1867. He received his undergraduate degree from Amherst College in 1888 and then left for Europe on a fellowship for seven years. Harvard awarded him a doctorate in 1899 and he joined the faculty of Smith College in 1900 as a Professor of Psychology. His research focused on perception and the senses, which was the topic of his book Studies in Space Perception published in 1901 by Longmans, Green and Co. Arthur Pierce was also an avid outdoorsman, often going on trips into the woods via canoe, motor or on foot. He died in Northampton, MA on February 20, 1914 of pneumonia.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of the research and lecture notes created by Arthur Henry Pierce during his tenure as a professor of Psychology at Smith College. The collection contains very little biographical or personal information. There are five photographs that show him standing on the Smith College campus, wearing rain gear and holding oars in preparation for an excursion and in formal portraits.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Arthur Henry Pierce papers were donated to the College Archives from a number of sources.
Pierce, Arthur Henry, 1867-1914
- General, 1900-1914 (Box 970, Folder 1)
- Notes, 1900-1914 (Box 970, Folder 2)
- Publications - "An Appeal from the Prevailing Doctrine of a Detached Subconsciousness" reprinted from the Studies in Philosophy and Psychology, commemorative volume dedicated to Prof. Charles E. Garman of Amherst College, Houghton Mifflin Co., undated (Box 970, Folder 3)
- Publications - Studies in Perception, New York: Longmans, Green and Co., 1901 (Box 970, Folder 4)
- Notes on Geometrical Illusions Vol. 1-3, 1900-1914 (Box 970, Folder 5)
- Notes on Laboratory Techniques Vol. 4, 1900-1914 (Box 970, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Advertisements, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Affective states, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Aphasia, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - Apperception, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - Association, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - Association of Diagnosis, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Attention, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Auditory Space Perception, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - The Blind, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Color Blindness, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Complication Experiments, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 11)
- Lecture Notes - Criminal Psychology, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 12)
- Lecture Notes - Drugs and Alcohol, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 13)
- Lecture Notes - Emotions, 1900-1914 (Box 971, Folder 14)
- Lecture Notes - Fatigue, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Fusion, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Habit, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - History of Psychology, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - Images, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - Inhibitions, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Instincts, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Intellectual Processes, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - Memory, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Mental Tests, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Perception, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 11)
- Lecture Notes - Porgandoff Illusion, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 12)
- Lecture Notes - Pleasure and Pain, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 13)
- Lecture Notes - Psychology of Advertising, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 14)
- Lecture Notes - Psychology of Testimony, 1900-1914 (Box 972, Folder 15)
- Lecture Notes - Philosophy 12 - Experimental Psychology, 1907-1908 (Box 973, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Reading process, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Reasoning, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - Sensation, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - The Senses of Sight, Hearing, etc., 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - The Soul, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Suggestion, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Synaesthesia, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - Telepathy, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Visual Space Perception, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Weber's Law, 1900-1914 (Box 973, Folder 11)
- Research on Apparent from of the heavens, etc, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 2)
- Data, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 3)
- Experiments, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 4)
- Notes, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 5)
- Original Records, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 6)
- Questionnaires, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 7)
- Reviews, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 8)
- Student observations, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 9)
- Summaries, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 10)
- Size Illusion of Celestial Magnitude Vol. 1-2, 1900-1914 (Box 974, Folder 11)